[Music]
button
Professor Dave and Chegg here the main
factor that influences reaction rates is
the concentration of each reactant we
can describe the relationship between a
reaction rate and the concentration of
its reactants by using something called
a rate law it will be important for us
to be able to derive these for any given
system but before we get to that let's
first make sure we understand precisely
what these are a rate law will take this
general form where the rate will be
equal to a rate constant K times the
product of the molar concentrations of
the reactants each raised to a
particular exponent these exponents are
almost always positive integers though
it is technically possible for them to
be fractions or negative numbers and
they are not evident from looking at the
Stoichiometry of the reaction let us
state that one more time for emphasis as
this is an extremely common error among
students the X exponents that we see
here in the rate law are not related to
and not necessarily equivalent to the
stoichiometric coefficients from a
balanced equation instead these
exponents must be determined
experimentally the rate constant is
independent of these concentrations but
it does depend on other parameters like
temperature and surface area the
exponents in the rate law tell us
something called the reaction order for
a reaction with two reactants the rate
law would look like this if m is 1 we
would say the reaction is first order
with respect to a if n is one it is
first order with respect to B if n is 2
it would be second order in B if it was
0 we would say it was Zero order in B
the overall reaction order is simply the
sum of the individual reaction orders so
if M and N are both one the overall
reaction order is two since one plus one
equals two
here are some examples of rate loss with
the reaction orders listed let's make
sure we can write these as they will be
important in our study of kinetics say
we are examining the reaction of
nitrogen dioxide and carbon monoxide to
form nitrogen monoxide and carbon
dioxide if we acquire kinetic data and
find that the reaction is second order
in NO2 and zero order in Co what will be
the rate law for this reaction well in
the rate law each concentration will be
raised to a certain power equal to the
reaction order for that reactant so
given the data we collected the
concentration of NO2 will be raised to
the second power and the concentration
of Co will be raised to the zero power
which makes it equal to one it can
therefore drop out of the rate law and
we will see that the rate law for this
reaction will simply involve the NO2
concentration squared let's try one more
for this reaction the rate law is as
follows what is the reaction order with
respect to each reactant and what is the
overall reaction order we can see from
the exponents that this reaction is
second order in no because of the two
and first order in H2 because if no
exponent is listed it's the same as an
exponent of one and the reaction is
therefore third order overall since two
plus one equals three
this may all seem pretty confusing but
for now we simply need to focus on these
definitions as we will soon put them to
good use when we derive reaction orders
experimentally which will make this
whole concept much more clear Professor
Dave for check see you next time
foreign